Etsy is slowly turning into slop.
It was the place for handcrafted,
high quality products, with
over 7 million sellers.
But now, many of those sellers…
aren’t making handmade stuff.
If you search for artwork, crochet patterns,
armor, or rugs, you'll find AI art everywhere.
Digital products spat out by ChatGPT… some
of them stealing from actual sellers on Etsy.
The share price is down 80%,
Buyers are down. Sellers are
down. Growth last year was just 2.6 percent.
Etsy's own AI decides what you see, and what
gets removed. And right now, it's removing
the actual sellers, whose work was stolen.
Yet, Etsy's CEO said "You couldn't run Etsy
without AI." And before that, he said "Being
good doesn't cut the mustard."
What on earth happened to Etsy?
When did Etsy turn to AI slop?
If you’re unfamiliar, Etsy is an ecommerce space
for selling handmade items, vintage items, and
craft supplies. Well, that’s what it used to be.
Its original mission was to “keep
commerce human,” and that quickly
drew in many creative entrepreneurs
who could sell something more personal.
They were more expensive, but you were supporting
a local artist or small business. Like you were
buying from someone in your neighborhood.
Someone’s own handmade art, or maybe something
wooden with a personal engraving,
or even a medieval knight’s helmet.
It felt like you were buying from someone who
loved their craft, and was really good at it.
To be clear, there are still a ton of fantastic
products made by great sellers on Etsy.
But things have changed a
lot in the past few years.
The pool of authentic sellers… is
shrinking. Because Etsy has implicitly
favored another type of seller.
Ironically, selling handmade stuff
is now one of the hardest things to do on Etsy.
A search for crochet patterns will pull dozens of
AI-generated images ahead of handcrafted images.
Etsy's policy allows AI-generated content,
and we’ll go more into that, don’t you worry.
But these patterns cost $2 to $10 and are meant
to instruct the buyer on how to create
the image featured on the store page.
But with dozens of these AI images
as the top results, many learners new
to crocheting are scammed. Because… it’s
AI. Of course it’s not going to be right.
That’s not shade at the buyers, not
everyone has a strong eye for AI.
But these stores have hundreds, and
some even thousands, of sales and,
at the same time, reviews warning others
not to fall into the scam like they had.
“The pattern looks nothing like the
picture that advertised the pattern.”
“The image is an AI-generated image, and I
will never purchase from this seller again.”
Some mix authentic pictures with
AI images to avoid suspicion.
“The first picture in the
listing is what makes you want
to buy the pattern, as it’s AI-generated.”
It goes far beyond crochet patterns though.
“Forced to buy from Amazon and Ebay
because AI slop has ruined etsy.”
Of course, these sellers will also just
lie about the condition of the products.
Oh that’s if you even get the product by the way.
“Shops may use AI-generated images that claim to
show handmade or custom items. The product may
not even exist. By the time you realize you’ve
purchased from a fake Etsy shop, the seller
has likely removed it from the platform,
potentially leaving you out of pocket
and vulnerable to identity theft with
limited options for recourse.”
These scams are called Vibescams.
When Etsy was asked for a statement, they
said: “We want our buyers to know we have
their backs — so in the rare case that
a shopper receives an item that does not
match the listing image or description, they
can open a case and receive a full refund
through our Purchase Protection Program.”
Yeah… “very, super rare occasion,” guys.
But this might not even be the worst
thing these resellers have done.
You know that amazing feeling
of a fresh, new Macbook?
One that’s still in top shape, still
buttery smooth and highly responsive?
But, the native systems aren't always the
best to maintain this, especially on Mac.
Soon enough your Mac or iMac becomes cluttered
and slow, and we just accept it as the new normal.
It doesn’t have to be this way.
CleanMyMac is an Apple-notarized solution for Mac
control, care, and space optimization, by MacPaw.
CleanMyMac helps you clear space,
reduce background strain, and
maintain steady performance,
without risky fixes or constant interruptions.
Install CleanMyMac and use the dashboard to
see what’s straining your Mac.
Use Smart Care to scan your Mac
and see what’s slowing it down.
Use the Space Lens to get a visual
map of the files taking up all the space.
Like a large video you forgot was there.
Use the Cleanup Tool to see all the
extra junk you have lying around,
like trash, cache, or duplicate files.
Or my favourite… the Applications tool,
to find unused apps. It’s amazing what kind
of bloatware makes its way onto your Mac.
And once your Mac is healthy,
CleanMyMac helps it stay healthy,
by scanning for Malware, with Protection Manager.
CleanMyMac has 4.7 stars on the App Store,
with over 29 million downloads. It has
an IF design award, and was featured in
Apples’ very own best apps for 2026 list!
You can also buy CleanMyMac with a one time
purchase, or if you like, a subscription.
Get your Mac back up to speed today! Click
the link below and use my code LOGICALLY for
20% off to try CleanMyMac for 7 days free.
Thank you to CleanMyMac for sponsoring this video.
Some will blatantly reuse images from sellers on
Etsy, and sell them on eBay or other platforms.
“I am a designer. My product has been stolen,
and the vendor has used AI to modify my image.
They are selling it on eBay. My sales for
this product have stopped, as the AI version
looks appealing, and theirs have soared! But
eBay doesn't accept that it has infringed my IP
rights! Help!! I'm really scared she's just going
to go through my whole catalogue. She's
adding multiple new patterns every day.”
I feel so bad for this seller.
But sadly, there’s something
Etsy has done, which makes this even worse.
Authentic sellers are now competing to rank
together with stores that copied their designs.
This has caused some sellers who started before
the AI boom to experience
a sharp decline in sales.
But this is just the tip of the iceberg.
These videos, are everywhere.
The Etsy market, is flooded with these listings.
They just assume because it’s on Etsy… buyers
believe that they are supporting a
local artist, especially those who
lack the discernment to tell it’s fake.
And boy, these get way, WAY worse.
It’s not just for AI either,
but also dropshipping.
Dropshipping isn’t inherently bad,
but on Etsy? The place for hand-made
products? It all feels a bit weird.
Mass-produced items on AliExpress or
Temu are sold as handmade products
for double or quadruple the price.
What happened?
What decisions and
changes caused Etsy to get so bad?
And, is all of it backfiring?
In 2012, Etsy made a commitment by becoming a
Certified B Corporation: "We believe that business
has a higher social purpose beyond simply profit."
This is basically a for-profit business,
but with higher standards for
social and environmental impact.
But soon, Etsy made a change.
In 2013, in an announcement made by
CEO Dickerson, it now allowed sellers to have as
many people as they needed to run their business,
as well as have someone else ship their
goods, and even have manufacturing partners.
This might sound awful, but… I
don’t think this was a bad change.
You can still make a design, an innovation,
a style, and partner with someone to produce
more of it to meet demand.
Etsy simply couldn't scale
if every seller had to make every product by
hand. Working with production partners can
still produce something unique, provided
the original idea belongs to the seller.
Not everyone was thrilled with this:
“Their moniker is, you know, a place
to buy handmade. It doesn't say a place to buy
factory-made,” and “It started out to be a place
where you could get something special, something
one-of-a-kind, something made by a human being.”
This change, would inevitably lead to
a gradual shift in sellers on Etsy.
By 2015, when it wanted to go public,
Dickerson could no longer ignore the concerns.
[Chad Dickerson, CEO, Etsy]: "I have heard
concerns that by allowing our sellers to
partner with responsible manufacturers,
we are diluting our handmade ethos."
He insisted that “the website still values
craftsmanship”, but not everyone was convinced.
"The decision to allow manufactured
products was one to improve Etsy’s revenue,
but it affected Etsy artisans detrimentally."
“They fundamentally changed the purpose of Etsy.”
“To stay true to my handmade ethos,
I had to move my business elsewhere.”
Then, Josh Silverman joined Etsy's board
in 2016 and began to make some changes.
Just, not the ones sellers were hoping for.
The board fired Dickerson and installed
Silverman as CEO instead.
22% of the workforce would be cut,
about 230 people. Granted, according to Etsy,
many of these roles were in middle management.
Etsy employees signed a petition, with
multiple demands, asking the company to
"Stand for more than just Profits"
But it seems like only one of
the demands was ever met.
And, to add insult to injury,
Later, in November, Silverman
dropped the B Corporation label.
“The company had the best of intentions,
but wasn't great at tying that to impact....
Being good doesn't cut the mustard."
“Etsy has lost their identity. It was
started for makers and other creatives,
and now is more of an online strip mall.”
But ironically, around this
time, Etsy had its big break.
The pandemic sent everyone home...
people started shopping online,
while others started side hustles.
And Etsy was built for this.
The total value of everything sold on
Etsy jumped from about $5 billion in
2019 to $12.2 billion in 2021. Its stock
price also skyrocketed to $274 per share.
It took advantage of cheap borrowing
and began expanding aggressively.
Within weeks, it spent nearly $2 billion. It
acquired Depop for $1.625 billion on June 2,
then Elo7 for $217 million on June 28.
Lots of money spent in less than a
month. But debt was cheap.
With all this new demand,
Etsy saw a new opportunity.
The transaction fee increased from 3.5% to 5%.
Sellers using Offsite Ads could also
be charged an additional 12% to 15%.
Those who didn't offer free shipping
became less visible in search results.
Then Etsy raised the transaction
fee again, from 5% to 6.5%.
It became so much that in April 2022,
over 20,000 sellers went on strike,
setting their stores to “vacation mode”.
In response, Etsy committed to investing
more into trust and safety, and to adding
50 human agents to enforce policies better.
But… in the end, the protest changed nothing.
Etsy kept the higher fees and things
soon got much worse.
So, when exactly did Etsy
become flooded with AI slop?
And, is Etsy dying?
If you’ve made it this far, you might like our
videos, so consider subscribing! We’re trying to
reach a million, and need your help. Thanks
Let’s take a look at the data.
From 2023 to 2025, Etsy has lost 5.5 million
active buyers and one million habitual buyers.
The total value of everything sold on Etsy has
fallen from $12.1 billion to $10.5 billion.
And this isn’t too surprising given the state
of Etsy today, and one big policy they changed.
The meaning of handcrafted
items has changed once again.
AI is now considered creative and has a dedicated
category for it: “seller-prompted AI creation.”
Sellers just have to disclose this.
This sounds ok if it’s enforced.
Because plenty just don’t disclose it.
Buyers have to painstakingly go through
every picture to get to something real.
But not only do many sellers use AI,
Etsy's platform uses AI too.
AI is now the algorithm. It uses LLMs to
deliver search results and recommendations.
But based on what we’ve seen recently,
it sure seems like these favor bright,
clickable AI images over the genuine listings.
At the same time, AI also polices the products.
To be clear, LLMs can be an amazing tool to
identify scams and fraud, and
remove AI content. It’s making
a huge difference on YouTube at the moment.
But, it might be doing the opposite on Etsy.
Not only does it leave up stolen listings,
but it’s now flagging the original,
authentic sellers, whose work has been stolen.
And a lot of the time, it can’t be appealed.
“My shop (was suspended, I guess because
some of my bestsellers photos were stolen
by Chinese companies with deleted watermarks
on them. I had over 30000 sales and started
my Etsy shop in 2017. I filled an appeal and
attached photos and video files showing that
my items are handmade. Unfortunately my appeal
was automatically closed in less than 3 minutes.”
“Hi, etsy has suspended my account after
suspending 3 of my listings for violating
etsys creativity policy. Everything I produce
is handmade and of my own design. My designs
and photos are currently being stolen by Chinese
wholesale websites such as temu, shein, Ali baba
and Ali express. I have contacted etsy support
numerous times, and this morning I woke up to
my shop being suspended. I have filed an appeal
but have lost so much hope and trust in etsy,
I'm worried this is the end of my etsy shop.
I've sold over 70,000 products with over 14,000
positive reviews with an average rating of 4.9”.
And a massive, more recent change by Etsy makes
this more interesting.
Before, their policy
gave room for using templated designs or
patterns, but now that has been deleted.
Every item now has to be “based
on a seller’s original design”.
So what counts as unoriginal?
Sellers who use licensed design bundles,
STL files, or pre-made AI prompt
packs instead of creating their own.
But, in reality, this doesn’t
actually hit AI products.
In fact, it really hits drop shippers and even
some genuine sellers who legally licensed STL
files or designs. If you come with your own
prompts, that’s technically “based on your
own design”.
Ironic.
So, is Etsy dying?
Well, some of the
company's biggest bets... haven't paid off.
Those Covid acquisitions led to over $1.1
billion in write-downs.
But Etsy's advertising
revenue actually increased in early 2026,
bringing in an additional $14.4 million.
Sellers are now paying more for each click.
But, overall growth has slowed dramatically,
falling to just 2.6% growth in 2025.
When growth is that low, it shows a plateau.
Etsy is squeezing those already on
the platform, but it seems to me
that buyers, and sellers, are leaving.
Those who care about handcrafted stuff,
have realized Etsy has become a worse Amazon.
And in a few years, I think Etsy is going
to pay the price for losing that loyalty.
Plus, for most people copying the AI funnel
to make money… it’s so saturated,
most don’t actually make money.
What a waste of everyone’s time.
With this video, I’m not saying to not use Etsy,
there are still great sellers there.
But, be careful when you shop online.
AI can be a great tool, but a lot of products
feel like they’re getting worse because of it.
One of them… is Windows.
Microsoft pushed their AI
CoPilot into about every possible part
of Windows they could, and it backfired.
Click this video to learn more.